<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>audio on Markus Engsner</title>
    <link>https://engsner.com/tags/audio/</link>
    <description>Markus Engsner (audio)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://engsner.com/tags/audio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Repairing a Technics SU-800 amplifier</title>
      <link>https://engsner.com/posts/su-800-repair/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engsner.com/posts/su-800-repair/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in February, I started repairing an old Technics amplifier we had lying around.
While it worked for a short while after being turned on, the sound quickly dropped out.
After some digging around, I found the service manual and schematic for it, and started troubleshooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I removed the amplifier from it&amp;rsquo;s casing, and reassembled it in a more debug-friendly way on my workbench
(see picture).
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://engsner.com/images/su-800/amplifier.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;The amplifier, reassembled without enclosure.&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The amplifier, reassembled without enclosure.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came across some old forum threads, which seemed to indicate that it could be a problem with a relay.
This turned out to be the case, and luckily I found a seller from Germany selling the same part,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebay.com/itm/112254403859&#34;&gt;SSY-126&lt;/a&gt;,
but with a transparent enclosure.
I ordered two pieces, but didn&amp;rsquo;t have the time to install it when it came in the mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://engsner.com/images/su-800/SSY-126.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Picture of relay&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The replacement relay I ordered off eBay.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a couple of months later, I finally found the time to take care of it.
I managed to (with some trouble) desolder the relay. I had to cut two of the legs of the replacement relay,
in order for it to fit.
Having soldered the new relay in to place, I tested the amplifier. It worked!
It was now time to reassemble the amplifier.
This was easier said than done, due to the input select buttons being very hard to get into place.
I did eventually manage to put them back, by lifting and rotating the main PCB back and forth,
while at the same time trying to push the buttons with some force.
Not the most elegant solution, but it worked.
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://engsner.com/images/su-800/relay-compare.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;The two relays next to each other.&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The old relay (right) and the new one (left)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I made a silly mistake, which cost me quite some time.
In my haste to get it back together, I never tested the amplifier before fully reassembling it.
So when I finally plugged it in and pressed the power button, nothing happened.
Time to take it apart again!
Turns out I had cut a jumper off between two of the first PCBs.
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://engsner.com/images/su-800/jumper-cable.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;A jumper cable between two of the PCBs.&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The solution!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

To remedy this, I soldered a short piece of 14 AWG wire in its place.
This seemed to work, and I reassembled it again.
This time, making sure to test it between each and every step.
Having put the last screw back in its place, I once again fired it up.
This time I was treated to some lovely music out of the connected speaker, and the repair was finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://engsner.com/images/su-800/final-picture.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;The amplifier powered on.&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Up and running!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>